Guide to the Alexander Mordecai Bickel Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- LEGISLATION, 1958-1974; Series VI; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  - Executive Information
    - Civil Rights-Civil Liberties Research Committee, Harvard Law School: memorandum on "Production of Information Bill", 1973 pre-November 16 (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - U. S. Senate: S. 2432, amended, and accompanying report, 1973 December 11 (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - School Desegregation
    - Louis C. Allen, Jr.; letter enclosing draft bill, 1970 February 20 (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Frank Dunbaugh, U. S. Justice Department: critique of draft bill, 1970 February 20 (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Martin H. Gerry and Bertram W. Carp: "Comments on Draft Provisions Proposed by Professor Bickel", [1970 Feb?] (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Richardson Preyer, U. S. House: speech, "What Happens Next in our Schools?", 1970 March 2 (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - A. Bickel: "Revised Draft", 1970 March 4 (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - Jack Greenberg, director-counsel, NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund: critique of A. Bickel's first draft, 1970 March 5 (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - Daniel P. Moynihan, White House staff: letters, 1970 March 5-11 (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - R. Preyer: H. R. 16484, 1970 March 16 (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - "Statement by the President on Elementary and Secondary School Desegregation" and "Background Briefing", 1970 March 24 (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - U. S. Commission on Civil Rights: "Statement … Concerning the 'Statement by the President…'", 1970 April 12 (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - R. Preyer: correspondence, 1970 April-May (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - L. Allen: correspondence, 1970 April-May (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - Richard M. Nixon: message to Congress on the Emergency School Aid Act of 1970, 1970 May 21 (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - U. S. House: H. R. 17846, 1970 May 27 (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - A. Bickel: statement before the U. S. House Education and Labor Committee, 1970 June 24 (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - R. Preyer: correspondence and testimony, 1970 July-August (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - William B. Spong, Jr., U. S. Senate: correspondence enclosing testimony of Clarence Mitchell, director, Washington Bureau, NAACP, 1970 August (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - Claiborne Pell, U. S. Senate: correspondence, 1970 August (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - L. Allen: letter enclosing desegregation plan of Burlington, N. C., 1970 August 19 (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - U. S. Commission on Civil Rights: "Analysis of S. 4167 …, Introduced by Senator Spong", 1970 August 21 (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - Internal Revenue Service: press releases on tax exemption of private schools, 1970 July 10-August 6 (Box 32, Folder 18)
    - Randolph W. Thrower, Commissioner of Internal Revenue: "Advance Draft" of statement before the U. S. Senate Select Committee on Equal Educational Opportunity, 1970 post-August 10 (Box 32, Folder 18)
    - A. Bickel: statement before the U. S. Senate Select Committee on Equal Educational Opportunity, 1970 September 24 (Box 33, Folder 19)
    - A. Bickel: "Comments and Criticisms of the Preyer-Spong Bill, S. 4167 and H. R. 16484, and Some Suggested Perfecting Amendments," before the U. S. Senate Select Committee on Equal Educational Opportunity, 1970 October 8 (Box 33, Folder 19)
    - W. Spong: correspondence, 1970 September-1971 January (Box 33, Folder 20)
    - A. Bickel: statement before the U. S. Senate Select Committee on Equal Educational Opportunity, 1971 June 15 (Box 33, Folder 21)
    - A. Bickel: "Busing and the Problems of Primary and Secondary Education", 1971 November 22 (Box 33, Folder 22)
    - Leonard Garment, White House staff: correspondence, 1971 November-1972 January (Box 33, Folder 22)
    - John Ehrlichman, White House staff: letter, 1971 December 29 (Box 33, Folder 22)
    - R. Preyer: letter enclosing "(Tentative Draft): A Bill to provide for affording equal educational opportunities for students in the Nation's public elementary and secondary schools", 1971 December 2 (Box 33, Folder 22)
    - "(Tentative Draft) #2: A Bill to provide for affording equal educational opportunities…", 1971 December (Box 33, Folder 22)
    - R. Preyer: correspondence, 1971 February-September (Box 33, Folder 23)
    - Morris K. Udall, U. S. House: correspondence, 1971 May (Box 33, Folder 23)
    - W. Spong: correspondence, 1971 July (Box 33, Folder 23)
    - A. Bickel: "National Educational Opportunities Act: Tentative First Outline Draft", 1971 August 30 (Box 33, Folder 23)
    - Emanuel Celler, chairman, U. S. House Judiciary Committee: correspondence, 1972 January-March (Box 33, Folder 24)
    - A. Bickel: statement before the U. S. House Judiciary Committee on "H. J. Res. 620 and Related Measures Proposing Amendments to the Constitution with Respect to the Transportation and Assignment of Public School Pupils", 1972 March 2 (Box 33, Folder 24)
    - U. S. House: printed bills on busing, 1971-1972 (Box 33, Folder 24)
    - R. Preyer: speech, press release, and H. R. 13552 ("A Bill to provide for affording equal educational opportunities …"), 1972 March 2 (Box 33, Folder 25)
    - Richard M. Nixon: press releases on busing and school desegregation, 1972 March 17 (Box 33, Folder 26)
    - U. S. House: H. R. 13915, 13916, 1972 March 20 (Box 33, Folder 26)
    - Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights under law: "Constitutionality of Student Transportation Moratorium Act of 1972", 1972 April 5 (Box 33, Folder 27)
    - Dave Stockdon, assistant to John B. Anderson, U. S. House: "The Nixon Equal Educational Opportunities Act, the Bickel draft and possible compromise", [1972 March-Apr?] (Box 33, Folder 28)
    - Irene Schecter, assistant to R. Preyer: letter, 1972 April 6 (Box 33, Folder 28)
    - [D. Stockdon?]: "A Bill to provide for affording equal educational opportunities …", [1972 Apr?] (Box 33, Folder 28)
    - Charles Alan Wright: "Statement …, on President's Program Concerning School Desegregation Remedies", 1972 April 27 (Box 33, Folder 29)
    - U. S. Justice Department: press release on benefits of proposed legislation, 1972 April 29 (Box 33, Folder 29)
    - Elliot L. Richardson, Secretary, U. S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare: correspondence, 1972 May-June (Box 33, Folder 29)
    - A. Bickel: statement before the U. S. House Education and Labor Committee, 1972 June 15 (Box 33, Folder 29)
    - R. Preyer: correspondence, 1973 February-April (Box 33, Folder 30)
    - Albert H. Quie, U. S. House: letter, 1973 March 7 (Box 33, Folder 30)
    - J. Bennett Johnson, Jr., U. S. Senate: letter, 1973 March 30 (Box 33, Folder 30)
    - R. Preyer, N. Udall, J. B. Anderson, and others: press release and subsequent correspondence with Clarence Mitchell, director, Washington Bureau, NAACP, 1973 July 31-August 7 (Box 33, Folder 30)
    - U. S. House Education and Labor Committee: Elementary and Secondary Education Amendments of 1973, 1973 September 5 (Box 33, Folder 31)
    - Charles W. Radcliffe, minority counsel, U. S. House Education and Labor Committee: "Description of Draft of Proposed Substitute for 'Anti-Busing' Amendments", 1973 October 3 (Box 33, Folder 31)
    - R. Preyer: H. R. 10991, 1973 October 17 (Box 33, Folder 32)
    - "Amendment to be Offered by Messrs. Esch, William, Ford, Huber and O'Hara to H. R. 69..", pre-1974 January 31 (Box 33, Folder 32)
    - J. Anderson: H. R. 13341 and speech, 1974 March 7 (Box 33, Folder 32)
    - R. Preyer: letters, 1974 March 27-June 10 (Box 33, Folder 32)
    - A. Bickel: notes and memorandum, 1971-1972, undated (Box 33, Folder 33)
    - Miscellaneous mimeographed matter, 1970-1971, undated (Box 33, Folder 33)
    - Clippings, 1970-1972 (Box 33, Folder 33)
    - U. S. Supreme Court and U. S. Court of Appeals, Fifth Circuit: printed opinions with passages marked, 1970-1971 (Box 33, Folder 34)
    - U. S. Congress: printed bills, 1970-1971 (Box 33, Folder 35)
  - Standing to Sue
    - A. Bickel: statement before the U. S. House Judiciary Committee on "a bill to provide effective procedures for the enforcement of the establishment and free exercise clauses of the First Amendment to the Constitution", 1968 March 28 (Box 33, Folder 36)
  - Subversive Activities
    - A. Bickel: memoranda on pending bills for Thomas J. Dodd, U. S. Senate, 1959 May (Box 33, Folder 37)
  - War Powers
    - George T. McKahin: "Cambodia: The Administration's Version and the Historical Record", 1970 post-May 1 (Box 33, Folder 38)
    - William H., Rehnquist, Assistant Attorney General: "The President's Constitutional Authority to Order the Attack on the Cambodian Sanctuaries," speech before the New York City Bar Association, 1970 May 28 (Box 33, Folder 38)
    - George S. McGovern, U. S. Senate: letters, 1970 May 15, August 28 (Box 33, Folder 39)
    - A. Bickel: draft proposal for American withdrawal from Indochina, 1970 May 27 (Box 33, Folder 39)
    - G. McGovern: press releases, 1970 August 26-28 (Box 33, Folder 39)
    - A. Bickel: statement before the U. S. House Foreign Affairs Committee, 1970 June 23 (Box 33, Folder 40)
    - David Cooke et al.: "Indochina: The Constitutional Crisis," Parts I and II, 1970 (Box 34, Folder 41)
    - Steering Committee of the Congressional Committee for a Vote on the War: publications, 1970 (Box 34, Folder 42)
    - Research materials, 1970 (Box 34, Folder 43)
    - Jacob K. Javits, U. S. Senate: address, "Who Makes War?", 1970 December 8 (Box 34, Folder 44)
    - Jacob K, Javits; correspondence, 1970 December 10-1973 June 21 (Box 34, Folder 44)
    - A. Bickel; statement before the U. S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee on S. 731, S. J. Res. 59, S. J. Res. 18, S. 95, and S. 1880, 1971 July 26 (Box 34, Folder 45)
      See also: tape recordings of this meeting transferred to the Historical Sound Recordings Collection
    - Jim ______: annotated draft, "War Powers Act of 1971" (Box 34, Folder 45)
    - Jim ______: annotated State Department memo, "Talking Points on S. 2956: War Powers", 1972 March 8 (Box 34, Folder 45)
    - A. Bickel and Arthur Schlesinger, Jr.; statements before the U. S. House Foreign Affairs Committee, National Security Policy Subcommittee, 1973 March 14 (Box 34, Folder 46)
    - U. S. House Foreign Affairs Committee, National Security Policy Subcommittee: correspondence, 1973 February 28-October 2 (Box 34, Folder 46)
    - A. Bickel: statement before the U. S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee on S, 440, 1973 April 11 (Box 34, Folder 47)
    - U. S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee; hearings on S. 440, 1973 April 11-12 (Box 34, Folder 48)
    - Thomas F. Eagleton, U. S. senate: correspondence, 1973 April 5-0ct 30 (Box 34, Folder 49)
    - Richard M. Nixon: veto message on House Joint Resolution 542, 1973 October 24 (Box 34, Folder 50)
    - Thomas E. Morgan and Clement J. Zablocki, U.S. House: "Reply to the President's Veto Message", 1973 November 1 (Box 34, Folder 50)
    - U. S. Senate Foreign Relations Committee: bills, reports, and press releases, 1969-1973 (Box 34, Folder 51)
    - H. S. Foreign Affairs Committee: bills, reports, and leaflets, 1970-1973 (Box 34, Folder 52)
  - Wiretapping
    - Thomas C. Hennings, Jr., U. S. Senate: correspondence, 1958 October-November (Box 34, Folder 53)
    - U. S. Senate Judiciary Committee: Hearing with Hennings-Bickel correspondence appended, 1959 July 9 (Box 34, Folder 53)
- POLITICS, 1967-1969; Series VII; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series VII, POLITICS, deals with Bickel's support for the presidential aspirations of Senators Charles H. Percy and Robert F. Kennedy in 1967 and 1968. His association with Percy (in conjunction with other Yale professors) was not a commitment to his hypothetical candidacy but merely an exploratory response to President Johnson's anticipated pre-emption of the Democratic nomination. The major items are Bickel's own writings: a lengthy letter naming the leading domestic and international problems of the nation and suggesting responses to them (1967 Oct 18), a defense of the negative income tax (1967 Nov 10), and three memoranda on crime control and civil disobedience. Percy responded favorably (Nov 3) to his moderate stance on withdrawal from Vietnam but criticized his ideas on race and poverty as narrowly economic and insufficiently sensitive to the value of local and personal initiative and participation.
  Bickel's support for the candidacy of Robert Kennedy was deep and unqualified, but the papers in this series reveal little about this foremost commitment of his political life, The major item is his memorandum for the senator's use, "Implementation of Federal Civil Rights Legislation." He explained his admiration for Kennedy and offered his final assessment of his career in several pieces in The New Republic (Series III, 1968-1969) and an address before the Consular Law Society (Series IV, 1968 Oct 30). He had opposed Kennedy's nomination as Attorney General, and the file for that article has notes on Kennedy's response in conversation with Gilbert A. Harrison and Bickel's undated reassessment in the light of Kennedy's performance in the office (Series III, The New Republic, 1961 Jan 9).
  Bickel occasionally recommended a colleague for a judicial or legal appointment, but the only other evidence of political activity on behalf of an individual is a letter to Connecticut Democratic leader Emilio Q. Daddario urging support of Joseph Duffey for the Senate nomination (Series I, 1970 Jun 4),
  - Charles H. Percy
    - Correspondence, 1967 October-1968 August (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - A. Bickel: "Law and Order", 1967 November 29 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - A. Bickel: "Law, Order, and Civil Disobedience", 1968 January 11 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - A. Bickel: "The Safe Streets and Omnibus Crime Act of 1968", 1968 May 4 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Addresses and statements, 1967-1968, undated (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Robert F. Kennedy
    - A. Bickel: "Implementation of Federal Civil Rights Legislation", 1968 March 19 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - California campaign: correspondence, notes, clippings, 1968 May 17-29 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Funeral memorabilia, 1968 June, 1969 June (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Position papers, undated (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Statement at Kansas State University, 1968 March 19 (Box 35, Folder 5)
- COMMITTEES, 1966-1974; Series VIII; 2 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Series VIII, COMMITTEES, consists of correspondence, memoranda, draft and final reports, speeches, and clippings documenting the activities of legal, political, and academic advisory bodies to which Bickel belonged or rendered aid. Several of these committees were created to propose reform of the Democratic Party or the federal courts. The others merely performed routine chores.
  Bickel was a member of the Democratic Party's Hughes Commission on the Democratic Selection of Presidential Nominees, but the papers in this section document little of its activity independent of his contribution. The major items are three drafts (the first not written by him) of his testimony on the Commission's behalf before the Credentials Committee of the 1968 Democratic National Convention; his memorandum on "Reforming the National Convention"; a preliminary version of the Commission's report, The Democratic Choice; and letters written during the following year by persons interested in implementing its proposals. Among Bickel's correspondents was Geoffrey Cowan, associate director of Commission staff, who transmitted a copy of his lengthy letter to Theodore H. White disputing White's account of Cowan's participation in The Making of the President, 1968.
  Roughly concurrent with his membership on the Hughes Commission in the summer of 1968, Bickel took part in the efforts of the Committee for the Formation of the New Party to offer an alternative to the anticipated choice between major-party presidential candidates Richard Nixon and Hubert Humphrey. The papers in this section consist of letters, committee mailings, research material on state election laws, and a Bickel memorandum on "Fourth Party Legal problems." It is not apparent how large a part he played in the committee's organization, but he met with members before July 31, recommended it to several correspondents, and agreed to serve as one of its candidates for presidential elector. He also supported a third-party candidacy in a speech before the Coalition for an Open Convention (Series IV, 1968 Jun 29) and in two final paragraphs he contributed to a New Republic editorial (Series III, 1968 Aug 3).
  Bickel was merely a consultant to the party's McGovern Commission on Party Structure and Delegate Selection, formed early in 1969, but the papers in this section provide a fairly full record of its activities as well as showing his personal contribution. Most of the items are letters, reports, and memoranda prepared by the Commission staff in multiple copies for the information of commissioners and consultants and sometimes the press as well. The memoranda for internal use supplement the public record by showing the staff's contributions to the development of proposals that eventually carried the endorsement of the entire Commission.
  Bickel's participation is documented mainly in a packet of materials he culled from his own Commission files and reproduced for the use of Theodore H. White in writing The Making of the President, 1972. His purpose was to trace the development of ideas about representation of minority groups and minority political views prior to the adoption in November 1969 of quotas for delegate selection, at which time he stopped collaborating with the Commission. (But see his New Republic editorial, Series III, 1970 Feb 7.) The items he selected have been kept with the covering letter. They include correspondence with Senator George McGovern and a memorandum of a conversation with him, notes on Commission and Commission staff meetings, and an exchange of letters with fellow consultant Richard Wade.
  Bickel was not affiliated with the party's O'Hara Commission on Rules, mate to the McGovern Commission, but merely testified before it. The papers in this section include his prepared statement, an exchange of letters with chairman James G. O'Hara, press releases, staff memoranda, reports, and copies of other witnesses' testimony.
  Bickel's other major stints of committee service were performed on behalf of the federal courts. In 1971 he participated in the Chief Justice's Special Advisory Group on Federal Civil Litigation; the following year, in the Study Group of the Federal Judicial Center on the Caseload of the Supreme Court. Notwithstanding the difference in name, both were formed at the request of Chief Justice Warren E. Burger, and both met under the auspices of the Federal Judicial Center. Bickel's participation began in the summer of 1970, when he helped Burger develop ideas for an address before the American Bar Association. His contribution is documented in a memorandum of a telephone conversation (Jul 20) and an eight-page letter (Jul 23). There is no copy of the draft he annotated and returned to Burger. Their correspondence on court reform extended through the life of both committees, though concentrated in the second half of 1970. Their letters on other subjects are in Series I.
  Both committees met several times in Washington but transacted much of their business by mail. The papers related to their activities (in the sections Civil Litigation Advisory Group and Caseload Study Group) consist mainly of research material, letters and memoranda exchanged among members and with Federal Judicial Center staff, Bickel's notes on group meetings, and draft and final recommendations. The notes on meetings of the caseload study group include summaries of statements made by Supreme Court justices appearing before the committee.
  There is no evidence of reaction to the civil litigation advisory group's "Suggestions for Improving the Process of Federal Civil Litigation," nor of efforts to implement its proposals except Burger's speeches and his correspondence with Bickel. The case is very different for the caseload study group's recommendation of a National Court of Appeals. Among the items documenting reception of this proposal are clippings from newspapers, magazines, and legal periodicals; letters of former Chief Justice Earl Warren and Circuit Judge Clement F. Haynsworth responding to premature revelations of the group's conclusions; a transcript of the press conference releasing the finished report; and speeches and reports by justices, lawyers, and professional associations. Bickel's efforts on behalf of the recommendations included collaborating with the American Bar Association's Special Committee on Coordination of Judicial Improvements (reports in this series; correspondence in Series I), taking part in a televised debate on "The Advocates" (Series IV, 1973 post-Oct 11), and writing The Caseload of The Supreme Court (Series II).
  The sections are in alphabetical order, as are the activities in Miscellaneous. The papers for each of those activities and the papers in every other section are in roughly chronological order except that items not related to any particular phase are at the end.
  - Caseload Study Group
    - Warren E. Burger: correspondence, 1971 August-September (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Bernard G. Segal: correspondence, 1971 December (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Paul A. Freund: correspondence, 1971 December-1972 January (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Members and staff: letters and memoranda, 1972 February 11-April 26 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Carl McGowan: letters, 1971 October 12 -1972 March 29 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - A. Bickel and Robert L. Stern: notes on meetings, 1972 May, June (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Members: letters and memoranda, 1972 May 8-June 28 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Robert L. Stern: "RLS Section with Respect to the Elimination of Appeals", 1972 July 11 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - A. Bickel: draft recommending a National Court of Appeals, 1972 July 11 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Peter D. Ehrenhaft: "Proposed chapter on internal improvements of the Court", 1972 July 12 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Staff: memorandum on statistics, 1972 July 14 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Peter D. Ehrenhaft: "Foreword", 1972 July 17 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - A. Bickel: "Second Draft", 1972 July 24 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Paul A. Freund: "Draft", [1972 Jul?] (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Draft report, 1972 August 31 (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - Members: correspondence, 1972 September 6-25 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - Albert Tate, Jr., member, Advisory Council on Appellate Justice: letters and memorandum, 1972 April 1-September 7 (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - Draft report, 1972 October 11 (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - Members: letters, 1972 October 18-November 15 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Eugene Gressman: letter, 1972 October 31 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Warren E. Burger: letter, 1972 November 8 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Arthur S. Miller: letter, 1972 November 8 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Earl Warren: letter, 1972 November 8 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Draft report, 1972 November 17 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - Members: letters, 1972 November 20-December 11 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Earl Warren: memorandum, 1972 November 8 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Clement F. Haynsworth: letters, 1972 November 20, December I1 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Transcript of press conference, 1972 December 19 (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - Frank J. Whalen, Jr.; letters, 1972 December 18, 20 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - William H. Dempsey, chairman, National Railway Labor Conference: correspondence, 1972 December 27-1973 January 8 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Warren E. Burger: letter, 1973 January 2 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Advisory Council on Appellate Justice:
      - "The Structure of the Federal Courts: Committee Draft No. 2", 1973 January 3 (Box 36, Folder 12)